## Jiaji Huang

CONTACT Information Baidu Research, 1195 Bordeaux Dr, Sunnyvale, CA 94089, USA

E-mail: huangjiaji@baidu.com

Tel: (919) 599-8156

Homepage: https://jiaji-huang.github.io

RESEARCH STATEMENT My PhD dissertation focuses on **statistical signal processing** and **machine learning**, with a special interest in understanding how **geometry of high dimensional space** impacts various tasks, including signal reconstruction, representation and classification.

My recent research interest lies in the intersection of **machine learning** and **natural language processing**. I am interested in understanding and improving the representations learned under weak supervision. Examples are pre-trained language models, their contextual embeddings and various language understanding tasks.

I usually formalize problems with a mathematical language, seek their solutions, and then work on performance guarantees.

EMPLOYMENT

July, 2016 — Aug., 2019 Research Scientist, Baidu Research Aug., 2019 — Now Senior Research Scientist and Research Lead, Baidu Research

## Representative Research Projects (inverse chronological order)

- Language models: methods, analysis and applications  $Key\ Results$ :
  - 1. Generalizing language models to unseen tasks: up to 13% improvement on token level tasks. Paper accepted at Neurips 2021; open source at task\_space
  - 2. Zero-shot pruning method, reducing  $\sim 70\%$  attention head, with performance loss < 5% on GLUE.
  - 3. Detection of Alzheimer's Disease via speaker's transcription. **1-st** place in Interspeech ADReSS challenge
  - 4. Identify and visualize clusters and isotropy in contextualized word embeddings
- Bilingual Lexicon Induction

Key results: State-of-art on MUSE benchmark by facebook; open source at HNN

- Large Margin Neural Language Models
  - $Key\ results$ : 1.11 WER reduction for speech recognition and 0.96 BLEU improvement for machine translation
- Improved optimization of CTC loss

Key results: smaller CTC loss by using estimated alignments

- Active learning for speech recognition

Key results: 50% fewer labels, but comparable accuracy

EDUCATION

## April, 2016 PhD, Electrical and Computer Engineering, Duke University

Thesis Advisor: Claude E. Shannon Award Recipient Robert Calderbank

July, 2011 B.S., Electrical Engineering, University of Science and Technology of China with Honor: Distinguished graduate, National Scholarship

Conference (Selected)

**J. Huang**, Q. Qiu, K. Church. Exploiting a Zoo of Checkpoints for Unseen Tasks. Neural Information Processing Systems (Neurips) 2021.

- Y. Bian, J. Huang, X. Cai, J. Yuan, K. Church. On Attention Redundancy: A Comprehensive Study. North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies (NAACL) 2021.
- X. Cai, J. Huang, Y. Bian, K. Church. Isotropy in the contextual embedding space: Clusters and manifolds. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2020.
- J. Yuan, Y. Bian, X. Cai, **J. Huang**, Z. Ye, K. Church. Disfluencies and Fine-Tuning Pre-Trained Language Models for Detection of Alzheimer's Disease. In Interspeech 2020.
- J. Huang, X. Cai and K. Church. Improving Bilingual Lexicon Induction for Low Frequency Words. In Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP) 2020.
- J. Huang, Q. Qiu and K. Church. Hubless Nearest Neighbor Search for Bilingual Lexicon Induction. In Proceedings of the 57th Conference of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) 2019.
- **J. Huang**, Y. Li, P. Wei and L. Huang. Large Margin Neural Language Model. In Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP) 2018.
- W. Wang , Z. Gan, W. Wang, D. Shen, **J. Huang**, W. Ping, S. Satheesh, and L. Carin. Topic Compositional Neural Language Model. International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2018.
- W. Zhu, Q. Qiu, J. Huang, R. Calderbank, G. Sapiro, and I. Daubechies, LDMNet: low dimensional manifold regularized neural networks. IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2018.
- **J. Huang**, Q. Qiu, R. Calderbank and G. Sapiro. Discriminative Robust Transformation Learning. Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), 2015.
- J. Huang, Q. Qiu, R. Calderbank and G. Sapiro. Geometry-aware Deep Transform. International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2015.
- L. Wang, J. Huang, X. Yuan, V. Cevher, M. Rodrigues, R. Calderbank, L. Carin. A concentration-of-measure inequality for multiple-measurement models, IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT) 2015.
- **J. Huang**, Q. Qiu, R. Calderbank, M. Rodrigues and G. Sapiro. Alignment with Intra-class Structure can imporve classification. 40th IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2015.
- **J. Huang**, X. Yuan, and R. Calderbank. Multiscale bayesian reconstruction of compressive X-Ray image. 40th IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2015.
- **J. Huang**, X. Yuan, and R. Calderbank. Collaborative compressive X-Ray Image reconstruction. 40th IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2015.
- X. Yuan and **J. Huang**. Polynomial-phase signal direction-finding and source-tracking with a single accoustic vector sensor. 40th IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2015.
- **J. Huang** and X. Ning. Latent Space Tracking from Heterogeneous Data with an Application for Anomaly Detection. Pacific-Asia Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining 2015.

## JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- **J. Huang**, Q. Qiu and R. Calderbank. The Role of Principal Angles in Subspace Classification. IEEE Transaction on Signal Processing, vol. 64, no. 8, 2016, 1933-1945.
- **J. Huang**, Q. Qiu, R. Calderbank and G. Sapiro. *GraphConnect*: A Regularization Framework for Neural Networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1512.06757, 2015.
- L. Wang\*, J. Huang\*, X. Yuan\*, K. Krishnamurthy, J. Greenberg, V. Cevher, M. Rodrigues, D. Brady, R. Calderbank, and L. Carin. Signal Recovery and System Calibration from Multiple Compressive Poisson Measurements, SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences (SIIMS), vol. 8, no. 3, 1923-1954, 2015. (\*: equal contribution)
- Y. Xie, **J. Huang**, and R. Willett. Changepoint detection for high-dimensional time series with missing data, IEEE Journal of Selected Topics on Signal Processing (J-STSP), vol. 7, no. 1, pp. 12-27. 2013.
- Y. Zhou, Z. Ye, and J. Huang. Improved decision-based detail-preserving variational method for removal of random-valued impulse noise, IET Image Processing, Vol. 6, no. 7, pp. 976-985, 2012.

### Workshops

- **J. Huang**, R. Child, V. Rao, H. Liu, S. Satheesh and A. Coates, Active Learning for Speech Recognition: the Power of Gradients. Workshop of Neural Information Processing Systems on Continual Learning and Deep Networks (NIPS-CLDL), 2016.
- **J. Huang** and R. Calderbank, Modulator design for binary classification of poisson measurements. UCL-Duke Workshop on Sensing and Analysis of High-Dimensional Data (SAHD) 2014.
- Y. Xie, **J. Huang**, and R. Willett. Multiscale online tracking of manifolds, 2012 IEEE Statistical Signal Processing Workshop (SSP).

### PATENT

- E. Battenberg, R. Child, A. Coates, C Fougner, J. Huang, J. Heewoo, A. Kannan, M. Kliegl, A. Kumar, H. Liu, V. Rao, S. Satheesh, D. Seetapun, A. Sriam, Z. Zhu. Systems and methods for principled bias reduction in production speech models. U.S. Patent No. 10,657,955.
- X. Ning, **J. Huang**, and G. Jiang, Online sparse regularized joint analysis for heterogeneous data, US20150095490 A1, 2015.

# Professtional Experience

## Senior Program Committee

• Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)

#### Reviewer for Journals and Conferences

- IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing
- Neural Information Processing Systems (Neurips)
- International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)
- Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)

### Research Intern at NEC Labs America

May — Aug. 2013 Anomaly detection on heterogeneous time series (Advisor: Prof. Xia Ning)

## AWARDS

 $Outstanding\ Researcher\ Award,$ Baidu Research, 2019

Duke graduate school Fellowship, 2011-2012 Distinguished Graduate, University of Science and Technology of China, 2011

National Scholarship, 2011